Guide to the Roy C. Trimiar letters, 1939-1943 RL.11894
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Roy C. Trimiar letters
1939-1943
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11894
0.6 Linear Feet
Roy C. Trimiar was an African-American U.S. Army veteran, who served as a private in the Q.M. Det. SC-CASC, Colored, and the Ser. Det. SC-4th, Colored, 1942-1943. He was born in Homer, Georgia and lived much of his life in Cooleemee, North Carolina. He was married to Lola Wood Trimiar (1909-1996). Collection primarily includes letters from Trimiar to his wife in Cooleemee and Mocksville, NC (89 items). The letters begin with their courtship (1939) in Cooleemee, but mainly date from Trimiar's service in the U.S. Army Colored Troops stationed at Fort Bragg, N.C., and Fort Oglethorpe, Ga.
Arrangement
Organized chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
Roy C. Trimiar (1901-1989) was an African-American U.S. Army veteran, who served as a private in the Q.M. Det. SC-CASC, Colored, and the Ser. Det. SC-4th, Colored, 1942-1943. He was born in Homer, Georgia and lived much of his life in Cooleemee, North Carolina. He was a retired employee of Erwin Cotton Mills in Cooleemee, and he had also worked at Cannon Mills Co. and Rose's Department Store in Salisbury. He was married to Lola Wood Trimiar (1909-1996), who was born in Tocoa, Georgia. They were both members of the Ervin Temple CME Church in Rowan County.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Roy C. Trimiar letters were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2001.
Collection Overview
Collection primarily includes letters from Trimiar to his wife, Lola Wood Trimiar, in Cooleemee and Mocksville, NC (89 items). The letters begin with their courtship (1939) in Cooleemee, but mainly date from Trimiar's service in the U.S. Army Colored Troops stationed at Fort Bragg, N.C., and Fort Oglethorpe, Ga. Topics include army life; his jobs; Sunday services; trips to town; concerns about money and (apparently late) payment of wages; opinions of the Japanese; hopes for a discharge because of his age; and strategies to avoid racism. The letters also demonstrate his concern for his wife and their home, including support for her social activities and worry over tight finances, food rationing, and her safety. Includes letters to Trimiar from Lola (17 items) and other friends, receipts, business correspondence, and his draft letter. Acquired as part of the George Washington Flowers Collection of Southern Americana.
United States. Army -- African American troops; African American soldiers; African American soldiers -- Correspondence; Soldiers -- Family relationships; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Social aspects -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation -- African Americans; Racism -- United States; United States -- Armed Forces -- African Americans; United States -- Race relations -- History -- 20th century; Fort Bragg (N.C.); Fort Oglethorpe (Ga.); Trimiar, Roy C., 1901-1989; Trimiar, Lola Wood, 1909-1996; George Washington Flowers Collection of Southern Americana
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1939 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1942 Jul. 20 - Aug 17 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1942 Aug. 21-31 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1942 Sept. 5-21 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1942 Sept. 22 - Oct. 23 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1942 Sept. 23 - Nov. 5 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1942 Oct. 27 - Nov. 10 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1942 Nov. 20 - Dec. 13 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1942 Dec. 14 - 1943 Jan. 4 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Lola, from Roy, 1943 Jan. 11 - Feb. 6 (Box 1)
- Correspondence general (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Roy, 1942 (Box 1)
- Roy Trimiar biographical information (Box 1)